Eli Broad papers
UCLA Library Special Collections
Eli Broad papers
1957-2011
2235
UCLA Library Special Collections
26.8 linear ft. (16 record cartons, 10 document boxes, 2 flat boxes, and 6 oversize flat boxes)
Eli Broad is an American entrepreneur and philanthropist. His philanthropy related to art and education in Los Angeles includes important contributions to the Museum of Contemporary Art in Los Angeles, the Broad Art Center at UCLA, and the Walt Disney Concert Hall. The papers include event files, business files, photographs and home movies, materials related to Broad's philanthropy, press clippings, and awards.
Broad, Eli
Restrictions on Access
COLLECTION STORED OFF-SITE AT SRLF: Open for research. Advance notice required for access. Contact the UCLA Library Special Collections Reference Desk for paging information.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
COLLECTION CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
COLLECTION CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this collection require the production of reference surrogates. To access audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
Biography/History
Eli Broad is a renowned business leader who built two Fortune 500 companies from the ground up over a five-decade career in business. He is the founder of both SunAmerica Inc. and KB Home (formerly Kaufman and Broad Home Corporation).
Today, Eli Broad and his wife, Edythe, are devoted to philanthropy as founders of The Broad Foundations, which they established to advance entrepreneurship for the public good in education, science and the arts. The Broad Foundations, which include The Eli and Edythe Broad Foundation and The Broad Art Foundation, have assets of $2.4 billion.
The Eli and Edythe Broad Foundation funds system-wide programs and policies that strengthen public schools by creating environments that allow good teachers to do great work and enable students of all backgrounds to learn and thrive. The Broad Foundation’s major education initiatives include the $1 million Broad Prize for Urban Education, The Broad Superintendents Academy and The Broad Residency in Urban Education.
The Broad Foundation also invests in advancing innovative scientific and medical research in the areas of human genomics, stem cell research and inflammatory bowel disease. In an unprecedented partnership with the Massachusetts Institute of Technology, Harvard University and the Whitehead Institute, the Broads in 2003 announced a $100 million founding gift to create The Eli and Edythe Broad Institute for biomedical research. The Institute’s aim is to realize the promise of the human genome to revolutionize clinical medicine and to make knowledge freely available to scientists around the world. They gave a second $100 million gift to The Broad Institute in 2005, and in 2008, they gave an additional $400 million to make the world’s leading genomics institute permanent.
Over the past four decades, the Broads have built two of the most prominent collections of postwar and contemporary art worldwide: The Eli and Edythe L. Broad Collection and The Broad Art Foundation. The two collections together include more than 2,000 works by nearly 200 artists. Since 1984, The Broad Art Foundation has operated an active “lending library” of its extensive collection. Dedicated to increasing access to contemporary art for audiences worldwide, The Broad Art Foundation has made more than 8,000 loans of artwork to nearly 500 museums and university galleries worldwide.
Mr. Broad was the founding chairman and is a life trustee of The Museum of Contemporary Art in Los Angeles, to which The Broad Foundation gave a $30 million challenge grant in December 2008 to rebuild the museum’s endowment and to provide exhibition support. He is a life trustee of The Museum of Modern Art in New York and of the Los Angeles County Museum of Art, where the Broads gave a $60 million gift to build the Renzo Piano-designed Broad Contemporary Art Museum, which opened in February 2008, and to fund an art acquisition budget. In August 2010, the Broads announced plans to build a contemporary art museum and headquarters for The Broad Art Foundation on Grand Avenue in downtown Los Angeles. The new museum, to be called The Broad, will be designed by Diller Scofidio + Renfro and is scheduled to open in early 2014.
Tireless advocates of Los Angeles, the Broads have championed the cultural and architectural vitality of the city. Committed to the belief that all great cities need a vibrant center, Mr. Broad was the visionary behind the development of Grand Avenue in downtown Los Angeles, which will blend residential, retail, cultural and recreational uses into a civic centerpiece to rival the main boulevards of the world’s greatest cities. In 1996, Mr. Broad and then-Mayor Richard Riordan spearheaded the fundraising campaign to build the Frank Gehry-designed Walt Disney Concert Hall, which opened to worldwide acclaim in October 2003. The Broads provided the lead gift to the Los Angeles Opera to create a production of Richard Wagner’s four-opera cycle Der Ring des Nibelungen that debuted in 2009—2010. They gave $10 million in 2008 to create an endowment for programming and arts education at The Eli and Edythe Broad Stage and The Edye Second Space at the Santa Monica College performing arts center.
From 2004 to 2009, Mr. Broad served as a Regent of the Smithsonian Institution by appointment of the U.S. Congress and the President. He is a Fellow of the American Academy of Arts and Sciences and in 1994 was named Chevalier in the National Order of the Legion of Honor by the Republic of France. Mr. Broad serves on the board of the Future Generation Art Prize. He received the Carnegie Medal of Philanthropy in 2007 and the David Rockefeller Award from the Museum of Modern Art in March 2009.
Strong believers in higher education, the Broads have further extended their philanthropy to a number of universities across the country. The Broad Foundation made a major contribution to the School of the Arts and Architecture at UCLA for The Eli and Edythe Broad Art Center. Mr. Broad is a life trustee at Caltech, where the Broads created the Broad Fellows Program in Brain Circuitry, gave the cornerstone gift to create the Broad Center for the Biological Sciences, and funded the creation of the Joint Center for Translational Medicine at Caltech and UCLA to advance experimental research into clinical applications.
In 2006, the Keck School of Medicine at the University of Southern California announced the creation of the Eli and Edythe Broad CIRM Center for Regenerative Medicine and Stem Cell Research. The Broads gave a major gift to UCLA for the Eli and Edythe Broad Center of Regenerative Medicine and Stem Cell Research, which opened in 2010. In 2008, the Broads gave a major gift to the University of California, San Francisco for the new headquarters of the Eli and Edythe Broad Center of Regeneration Medicine and Stem Cell Research. Mr. Broad has also served as chairman of the board of trustees of Pitzer College and vice chairman of the board of trustees of the California State University system.
In 1991, the Broads endowed The Eli Broad College of Business and The Eli Broad Graduate School of Management at Michigan State University (MSU), where Mr. Broad graduated cum laude in 1954. In June 2007, the Broads announced a $26 million gift to create the Eli and Edythe Broad Art Museum at MSU, and they gave an additional $2 million to the project in January 2010. The museum will open in November 2012.
Mr. Broad is also a bestselling author with the publication of his first book, “The Art of Being Unreasonable: Lessons in Unconventional Thinking,” released by Wiley & Sons in May 2012.
The Broads reside in Los Angeles and have two grown sons.
Source: Eli Broad's website: http://elibroad.com/biography/.
Scope and Content
The Eli Broad papers range from 1957-2011, with the bulk dating from 1982-2010, and include materials related to his professional, philanthropic, and personal life. Among these materials are event files, including manuscripts of speeches Broad gave, invitations, seating arrangements, menus, and related correspondence. The business files include annual reports, a 25th anniversary scrapbook for Kaufman and Broad, Broad’s calendars and planners, five years of Broad’s daily itineraries and phone messages, and itineraries and correspondence related to his travel plans. The photographs and home movies series include photographs of Eli and Edythe with various politicians and celebrities and family photographs. The collection also contains press clippings, awards, and materials related to Broad's philanthropy, such as press kits, donor outreach materials, and architectural schematic designs and plans.
UCLA Catalog Record ID
UCLA Catalog Record ID: 7714750
Broad, Edythe; Broad, Eli
Container List
- Event files., 1993-2004.
  Scope and Content
  The event files contain materials related to parties and events the Broads hosted and attended. These materials include invitations and correspondence, seating charts, tax forms, menus, and other party planning paperwork, as well as manuscripts of speeches Broad gave. Among the events represented are the 1993 presidential inauguration, dinners with President Clinton, and Eli’s 70th birthday celebrations.
  Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
  SERIES CONTAINS DIGITAL MATERIALS: Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Events, 1993-2004. (Boxes 1-3)
    Event materials include correspondence, seating charts, tax forms, and other party planning paperwork, including materials related to the 1993 presidential inauguration, dinners with President Clinton, and Eli's 70th birthday celebrations.
    Box 1 includes one floppy disk related to the 1992 presidential inauguration of Bill Clinton and Al Gore.
    Box 1 contains one floppy disk.
    Special equipment or further processing may be required for viewing. To access digital materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Events, 2004-2010. (Boxes 3-5)
    Box 5 contains 1 CD and 1 DVD with digital materials.
    Event materials include correspondence, seating charts, budgets, and other party planning paperwork, including materials related to Broad's 75th and 80th birthday celebrations, the 2009 presidential inauguration, and a fundraiser for Congressman Sandy Levin. Also includes 80th birthday cards.
    In Box 4, Edythe's 70th birthday file includes black and white photographs. In Box 4 there are also ten DVDs relating to Eli's 75th birthday as well as the Koons installation and set-up.
    Box 5 contains a DVD of Inaugural event photos from 2013 from the Inaugural Gala, a CD of photographs from Eli's 80th birthday party in 2013, and a DVD from 2013 for Eli's 80th birthday entitled "LA's Worst Actor."
  - Speeches., Circa 1979-2001.. (Boxes 8-9)
    Includes annotated speeches given by Broad at Michigan State University and other organizations and correspondence for speeches Broad declined and accepted.
  - Invitations. (Boxes 18, 20)
    Box 18 contains invitations to benefits and to personal social functions, as well as sample invitations for events hosted by the Broads. It also contains an invitation to a party entitled "Spellbinding" the Broads held in June of 2013. The invitation is enclosed in film canister embossed with "Spellbinding" and labeled "Director's Cut."
    Box 20 contains an invitation to Eli's 70th birthday party, which came inside of a wooden crate bolted shut. The following messages are printed on it: "June 6. 1933," "Fragile: Handle with Care: High Claim Value," "Instructions enclosed," and images of an arrow pointing up and a martini. The invitation is printed on metal with a photo of Eli as a baby.
- Business files. (Box 13)
  The business files contain materials related to Broad’s professional life, including scheduling. The files consist of annotated calendars and planners, daily schedules annotated with phone messages, travel itineraries and correspondence, a Kaufman and Broad 25th anniversary scrapbook, and a transcript of the House & Home Distribution Roundtable. They also include annual reports for SunAmerica; American International Group, Inc.; Kaufman and Broad, Inc.; and Broad Inc.
  - Phone call files, 2007-2011. (Box 9)
    Annotated daily schedules with phone messages and scheduled phone calls and other meetings.
  - Travel files.., 2004-2011.. (Boxes 11-12)
    These files include correspondence, itineraries, and clippings related to Broad's travel plans.
  - Published annual reports, 1983-84; 1986-1994; 1996-2001. (Box 12)
    Annual reports for SunAmerica; American International Group, Inc.; Kaufman and Broad, Inc.; and Broad Inc.
  - House & Home Distribution Roundtable., 1966 February 8-9.. (Box 10)
    A bound copy of a transcript. 315 pages.
  - Desk calendars., Circa 1968-1979.. (Box 21)
    11 checkbook sized annotated calendars. 12 rolodex-style annotated hourly calendars. 3 week-at-a-glance calendars.
  - Scrapbook: Kaufman and Broad, Inc. 25th anniversary celebration, 1982. (Box 18)
- Photographs and home movies.
  The photographs and home movies include photo albums of the Broads with politicians and celebrities, including the Clintons; portraits of Eli and Edythe taken by Annie Liebovitz; and digitized family photographs and videos.
  SERIES CONTAINS AUDIOVISUAL MATERIALS: Audiovisual materials in this series require the production of reference surrogates. To access audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Photograph albums., Circa 1990s.. (Boxes 13-15)
    Six albums of photographs from events with politicians and celebrities, including Bill and Hillary Clinton. With occasional annotations.
    Box 13 contains three albums marked March ’98 VP Gala, March '99, and Dr. Armand Hammer Hosts a Luncheon for Former President Jimmy Carter.
    Box 15 contains two albums, including one related to the Democratic Senatorial Campaign Committee.
  - Photographs. (Boxes 14, 16)
    Digital:
    Box 16 contains four CDs.
    Audiovisual:
    4 CDs or DVDS.
    Box 16 contains four CDs. Audiovisual materials in this box require the production of reference surrogates. To access audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
    Titled folders of photographs covering subjects such as Broad's childhood, UCLA Broad Art Center, and Broad's 60th birthday. Box 14 contains photographs of Edythe and Eli from 2002 by Annie Leibovitz. Includes 4 CDs.
  - Broad home videos and photographs., 1957-1967, 1972, 1983, 2004. (Boxes 16-17)
    Box 16 contains: 5 CDs, an iPod, and one hard drive.
    Box 17 contains: 11 CDs.
    Box 17 contains: 8 mini DVs and 16 CDs and DVDs.
    Audiovisual materials in this box require the production of reference surrogates. To access audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
    DVDs of home videos, CDs of photos and slideshows, Mini DV, slides, an iPod birthday party invitation, printouts of disc contents, and a hard drive and cables. DVDs include a video for Broad's 80th entitled Eli Broad as LA's Worst Actor. In addition, there are 7 empty reels of Super8 film, 5 empty reels of color movie film, 10 empty reels of Kodachrome movie film, and 6 empty metal reels of film.
  - Disney Hall photograph., 2003. (Box 34)
- Creative and philanthropic project files.
  The creative and philanthropic project files consist of materials related to Broad’s foundations and other philanthropic ventures and related to the book he wrote, The Art of Being Unreasonable. These files include press kits for the Museum of Contemporary Art, the Broad Contemporary Art Museum, The Broad Foundation, and the Eli Broad Family Foundation; a book about Broad’s art collection; and international editions of The Art of Being Unreasonable. The philanthropic project files also include blue prints and schematic designs for the Michigan State University design competition and the Broad Collection.
  - Broad Contemporary Art Museum press kit. (Box 10)
  - The Broad Foundation and The Eli Broad Family Foundation press kits., 1989, 2002. (Box 10)
  - Jasper Johns to Jeff Koons: Four Decades of Art from the Broad Collections.. (Box 20)
    Scope and Contents note
    Hardcover book.
  - The Art of Being Unreasonable international editions. (Box 24)
    This includes two paperback books, one hardcover book, and an inlaid order form. The languages represented are Portuguese, Korean, and Japanese.
  - Eli and Edythe Broad Art Museum at Michigan State University design competition designs. (Box 32)
    These designs include 5 books of plans by various architects, correspondence regarding the MSU Broad Art Museum, a printout of presentation slides by Zaha Hadid Architects, a clipping regarding the design competition, a CoopHimmelB(L)au photography CD, and a DVD of an animation by William Pederson.
    Box 32 contains one CD.
    Box 32 contains one DVD. Audiovisual materials in this box require the production of reference surrogates. To access audiovisual materials you must notify the reference desk in advance of your visit.
  - Broad Collection schematic designs. (Boxes 29-31, 34)
    Boxes 29 and 34 include schematic designs and design development for the Broad Collection, the Broad Parking Facility, the Broad Museum, and the Broad Garage. Architects include Choate Parking Consultants, Diller Scofido & Renfro, Gensler, and IDG Parkitects. Box 30 includes books of designs and plans for the Broad Art Foundation museum and art storage facility. Box 31 includes architectural plans for the Broad Collection.
  - Museum of Contemporary Art materials. (Box 24)
    These materials include an issue of Philanthropy Magazine, 3 folders of press releases, a prospectus for prospective donors, Reimagining Grand Avenue prospectus, an invitation to the 2010 MOCA Happening annual Gala, and an art object (book) for the 30th anniversary Gala for the MOCA.
  - Los Angeles County Museum of Art architectural designs. (Boxes 33)
    This box contains the Los Angeles County Museum of Art Integrated Design and Multidisciplinary Engineering book of architectural designs and Los Angeles County Museum of Art Renzo Piano Building Workshop schematic design report.
  - Broad Center for Biological Sciences at California Institute of Technology architectural plans. (Box 31)
- Press clippings.
  The press clippings are organized by year and relate to Broad’s business and philanthropic ventures.
  - Clippings, 1998-2007. (Box 6)
    Clippings span topics such as The Broad Foundations, education, Los Angeles, and the economy. They include interviews with, profiles of, and mentions of Broad.
  - Clippings, 1993-1997. (Box 7)
    Clippings span topics such as art collection and investing and include mentions of Broad in the media. Includes a 1997 article by Broad "25 Ways to Make L. A. Grow." This box also includes a VHS entitled "A Tribute to Eli Broad" from the 1996 Annual Real Estate Finance and Investment Conference.
    One VHS.
  - Clippings, circa 1980-1992. (Box 8)
    Clippings span topics such as SunAmerica and real estate and include mentions of Broad in the media. Also includes correspondence from journalists.
  - Clippings., 1968, 1971, 1983-1986, 1990. (Box 14)
  - Election day newspapers.. (Box 24)
    Approximately 1 document box in size.
  - Clippings, circa 1977-1987. (Boxes 19, 22, 23, 28)
  - Museum of Contemporary Art Los Angeles News Clippings.., 1980-1984, 1986-1987. (Boxes 23, 25, 33)
- Awards and recognitions.
  The awards and recognitions consist of honors Broad received, including the first award Broad was given in Los Angeles, the City of Hope Man of the Year award. Also included is a pin given by The Broad Foundation to Broad Scholars.
  - Awards and recognitions. (Boxes 20, 26, 27, 34)
    Mounted awards and proclamations from Governor Gray Davis, Senator Dianne Feinstein, and others. Plaques and framed awards from the United States Congress, House & Home magazine, and others. Also includes the first award Broad received in Los Angeles, the City of Hope Man of the Year award, which is a large bound book. Also includes a certificate of completion of Army General School by Private Eli Broad and his report of standing from Michigan State College. Includes a pin given to Broad Scholars by The Broad Foundation in 1999. Box 34 includes 14 awards and recognitions, including a certification from the American Institute of Certified Public Accountants and a certificate naming Broad a Trustee of California State University and Colleges.